A Finding Aid to the Jacques Lipchitz papers and Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1910-2001, bulk 1941-2001, in the Archives of American Art AAA.lipcjacq2
Archives of American Art
- Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1961-2001; Series 2; 43.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-67, OV 68-69
  - Film Projects Regarding Jacques Lipchitz, 1971-2001; 2.5; 28.2 Linear feet Boxes 22-46, 53-65, OV 69
    - Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001; 2.5.2
      - Audiovisual Materials (Box 31)
        - Segments (Box 35)
          - Miami and Joe Harrison Interview, Mother and Child, Notre Dame de Liesse, circa 1971-1981; (5 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 8)
          - New Segments, Opening, Paracelles, Pollution Affects Art, Storytelling, circa 1971-1981; (7 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 9)
          - Yulla Lipchitz/Israel, circa 1971-1981; (6 film reels: workprint, in 1 oversized film can in Box 64) (Box 36, Item 10)
          - Unidentified Segments, circa 1971-1981; (7 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 11)
        - Miscellaneous Trims, circa 1971-1981 (Box 36, Item 12)
          workprint and soundtrack in 1 film can
        - Segments, continued (Box 37)
          - Art Is Eternal, Banker's Economy, Bellerophon, circa 1971-1981; (5 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 1)
          - Bellerophon, circa 1971-1981; (4 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 2)
          - Birth and Unity, circa 1971-1981; (4 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 3)
          - Birth and Unity, Cubism, FF, First come to America, circa 1971-1981; (5 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 4)
          - Gursenski, James Joyce, Last Embrace, circa 1971-1981; (6 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 5)
          - Man Getting Better, Miami and Joe Harrison, circa 1971-1981; (3 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 6)
          - New Segments, Notre Dame de Liesse, Pollution Affects Art, Storytelling, circa 1971-1981; (6 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 film can) (Box 37, Item 7)
          - New Segments, Transparencies/Jacob and the Angel, Yulla/Israel, circa 1971-1981; (6 film reels: soundtrack, in 1 oversized film can in Box 64) (Box 37, Item 8)
          - Unidentified Segments, circa 1971-1981; (13 film reels: soundtrack, in 2 film cans) (Box 37, Item 9)
      - Demonstrations (Box 38)
        - Metropolitan Museum, 1972 June 11; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 38, Folder 1)
        - City University of New York, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 2)
        - Exxon Education Foundation, 1979; (2 folders, script and 1 videocassette: U-Matic) (Box 38, Folder 3-4)
      - Exhibition Materials (Box 38)
        - Magnetic Strips, circa 1971-2001 (Box 38, Folder 5)
          in shoebox
        - Segment Boards, circa 1972-2001 (Box 38, Folder 6)
          Oversized item in OV 69
        - Signs, circa 1972-2001 (Box 38, Folder 7)
        - Topic Cards, circa 1972-2001 (Box 38, Folder 8)
      - Production Notebooks, circa 1999 (Box 38, Folder 9)
      - Production Files, circa 1972-2001; 4 Folders (Box 38, Folder 10-13)
      - Program Code, circa 1999; 2 Folders (Box 38, Folder 14-15)
      - Program Guide, 1998-1999 (Box 38, Folder 16)
      - Questions and Answers (Box 39)
        - Handwritten Question Cards, circa 1972; 6 Folders (Box 39, Folder 1-6)
        - Printouts of All Questions, 1973; 2 Folders (Box 39, Folder 7-8)
        - Printouts of Questions with Answers, 1973; 4 Folders (Box 39, Folder 9-12)
        - Printed Questions on Sorting Cards, circa 1973; 3 Folders (Box 39, Folder 13-15)
        - Annotated Questions, circa 1972-2001; 2 Folders (Box 40, Folder 1-2)
        - Coded Questions, circa 1972-2001; 2 Folders (Box 40, Folder 3-4)
      - Source Book, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 5)
      - Source Book, circa 1973 (Box 40, Folder 6)
      - Source Book, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 7)
      - Source Book, 1990 (Box 40, Folder 8)
      - Source Book, circa 1998 (Box 40, Folder 9-11)
      - Source Book, circa 2000 (Box 40, Folder 12-14)
      - Source Book, Krannert Art Museum, 2001 (Box 40, Folder 15-16)
      - Source Book, Reels A-D and Parts I and II Revised Script, undated (Box 40, Folder 17)
      - Technical Drawings of Interactive System, circa 1972-2001 (Box 40, Folder 18)
      - Transcript of Picasso Segment, circa 1972-2001 (Box 40, Folder 19)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Introduction (workprint from Box 31, item 1) (Box 57)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Birth-Cubism (workprint from Box 31, item 2) (Box 57)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Introduction (soundtrack from Box 31, item 1) (Box 58)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Birth-Cubism (soundtrack from Box 31, item 2) (Box 58)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Transparencies-Jacob and the Angel (soundtrack from Box 31, item 3) (Box 58)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Transparencies-Jacob and the Angel (workprint from Box 31, item 3) (Box 59)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Mother-Virgin (workprint from Box 31, item 4) (Box 59)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Mother-Virgin (circa 1972) (soundtrack from Box 31, item 4) (Box 60)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Reel C (1982) (soundtrack from Box 34, item 3) (Box 60)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Reel D (1982) (soundtrack from Box 34, item 4) (Box 60)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Reel C (1982) (workprint from Box 34, item 3) (Box 61)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Reel D (1982) (workprint from Box 34, items 4) (Box 61)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Miscellaneous Reels, Q+A Reel C (from Box 35, items 4) (Box 62)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Miscellaneous Reels, Reel II, Part 1 (from Box 35, item 5) (Box 62)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Segments, Columbine (workprint, from Box 36, item 2) (Box 63)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Segments, Last Embrace (workprint, from Box 36, item 6) (Box 63)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Segments, Transparencies-Jacob-Yulla (workprint, from Box 36, item 10) (Box 64)
      - Oversized Audiovisual Materials, Segments, New Segments, Transparencies-Jacob, Yulla (soundtrack, Box 37, item 8) (Box 64)
      - Oversized Exhibition Materials, Segment Board and Signs (from Box 38, items 6-7) (Box 69)
    - Jacques Lipchitz Documentary, 1972-1994; 2.5.3
      This subseries contains audiovisual and a few paper records related to the documentary Bassett produced about Jacques Lipchitz. The first version was created in 1972 in tandem with the Metropolitan Museum of Art's Lipcthiz retrospective exhibition. The documentary was updated in 1977 with footage added from the posthumous large-scale sculpture installations, and then revised again in 1991.
      The subseries includes multiple finished versions of the documentary in their presentation and distribution formats (film and video), and pre-print master elements of the finished versions (A+B roll and internegative; master from which distribution copies are made). Also found are production elements made at different stages of production and revision, excerpts of the finished film compiled for publicity, and two pieces of television coverage of the installation of Bellerophon Taming Pegasus that use Bassett's footage.
      Some of the film cans contain paper lab records for prints and edits created over the years.
      Additional records related to the documentary are found in Subseries 2.2.1 Business Records, Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, and Subseries 2.3, Printed Materials.
      One copy of the documentary has been digitized for research use.
      - Finished Versions (Box 41)
        - Presentation Copy, circa 1972; (2 videocassettes: U-Matic) (Box 41, Item 1)
        - Presentation Copy, 1977; (2 film reels) (Box 41, Item 2)
        - Presentation Copy, 1977; undated; (2 duplicate videocassettes: U-Matic) (Box 42, Item 1)
        - Presentation Copy, Short Version, 1989; undated; (1 film reel and 2 duplicate videocassettes: U-Matic and VHS; oversized film reel housed in Box 65) (Box 42, Item 2)
        - Presentation Copy, 1991; (1 film reel and 2 duplicate videocassettes: U-Matic and VHS; oversized film reel housed in Box 65) (Box 42, Item 3)
        - Pre-Print Master Elements (Box 43)
          - Reel 1, undated; 1972; (4 film reels: A+B Roll picture and 2 soundtrack reels) (Box 43, Item 1)
            (Can with A Roll contains film lab records)
          - Reel 2, 1972; 1974; 1976; (4 film reels: sound effects tracks A-D) (Box 43, Item 2)
          - Reel 2, 1972; 1974; 1976; (8 film reels: A+B Roll picture and 6 unmixed soundtrack reels) (Box 44, Item 1)
          - Reels 1 and 2, 1978-1980; 1976; (4 film reels: internegative picture and soundtrack) (Box 45, Item 1)
          - Reel 1, 1991; (2 film reels: internegative picture and soundtrack) (Box 45, Item 2)
      - Production Elements (Box 45)
        - Original Ending, circa 1972; (9 film reels: A+B Roll picture, internegative picture and soundtrack, and answer print, housed in 2 film cans) (Box 45, Item 3)
        - Revised Ending, 1977; (2 sound tape reels) (Box 45, Item 4)
        - Parts I, II, and III, circa 1977; (3 sound tape reels) (Box 45, Item 5)
        - Titles, 1977; (1 film reel) (Box 45, Item 6)
        - Pre-print with Visible Time Code, 1991; (3 videocassettes: U-Matic) (Box 46, Item 1)
      - Excerpts (Box 46)
        - Two Segments: Bellerophon Taming Pegasus, Freedom of Expression, circa 1977; (1 videocassette: U-Matic) (Box 46, Item 2)
        - Stills and Segments for Random House Presentation, 1994; (1 videocassette: Betacam SP) (Box 46, Item 3)
      - Television Coverage (Box 46)
        - Today Show, 1977 June 16; (1 film reel, 1 duplicate videocassette: U-Matic, film reel housed in Box 65) (Box 46, Item 4)
        - News Story on Bellerophon Taming Pegasus Installation, 1977; (1 film reel, 1 duplicate videocassette: U-Matic, film reel housed in Box 65) (Box 46, Item 5)
          (Film can contains film lab records)
      - Finished Versions, Presentation Copies, 1989 and 1991 (2 film reels from Box 42, items 2-3) (Box 65)
      - Television Coverage, Today Show (from Box 46, item 4) (Box 65)
      - Television Coverage, News Story on Bellerophon Taming Pegasus Installation (from Box 46, item 5) (Box 65)
  - Other Projects, 1961-2000; 2.6; 5.2 Linear feet Boxes 47-52, 66-67
    This subseries contains audiovisual material and a few paper records from projects unrelated to Jacques Lipchitz that were also found among Bruce Bassett's papers. Other projects by Bruce Bassett include audiovisual recordings from projects about Isamu Noguchi, Sidney Lifchez, Auguste Rodin, the Storm King sculpture center, IBM, and others, listed below. The Lifchez documentary is well-documented, but records of other projects in the series are incomplete and fragmentary. Also found are projects by others, including a draft of a screenplay, two news films of John F. Kennedy, and several other film titles. The films Dream on Monkey Mountain and Man Is My Name were made by others but were produced or aired by NBC, where Bassett worked, and he may have been involved in their production or broadcast.
    - Projects by Bruce Bassett (Box 47)
      - A House for Someone Unlike Me with Sidney Lifchez (Box 47)
        - Finished Version, 1984; (1 videocassette: U-Matic, 2 duplicate videocassettes: VHS) (Box 47, Item 1)
        - 15-minute Version, 1984; (2 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 47, Item 2)
        - Camera Tapes 1-18, 1984; (18 of 25 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 47, Item 3-20)
        - Camera Tapes 19-25, 1984; (7 of 25 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 48, Item 1-7)
      - IBM Project (Box 48)
        - The Massey Ferguson Project, 1983; (3 film reels: color negative, internegative, and soundtrack) (Box 48, Item 8)
          (Color negative can contains film lab records)
        - Interactive Marketing Project, 1982; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 48, Item 9)
        - Computer Search and Retrieval Instructions, undated; (1 sound tape reel and paper file) (Box 48, Item 10)
        - Interviews, 1982; (1 sound cassette, 2 annotated, empty cassette cases) (Box 48, Item 11)
        - Unidentified Video, Reels 3 and 4, 1986 June 17; (2 videoreels: 1 in.) (Box 49, Item 1-2)
      - Isamu Nogochi Project (Box 49)
        - Sound Rolls 1-3, 1978 September 12-15 (Box 49, Item 3-5)
        - Momo Taro, 1979 January 4; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 49, Item 6)
        - Detroit Fountain, circa 1978-1979; (1 sound cassette) (Box 49, Item 7)
        - Honolulu Rolls 2, 5, and 7, circa 1978-1979; (4 sound cassettes) (Box 49, Item 8-10)
          (2 cassettes are marked "roll 2")
        - First Half, Soundtrack, undated; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 49, Item 11)
        - Unidentified Video, undated; (1 video reel: 2 in. housed in Box 67) (Box 49, Item 12)
          (Label reads "1-12 Lipchitz, 13-24 Noguchi")
      - Rodin-related Interviews (Box 50)
        - Jean Bernard, undated; (2 sound cassettes) (Box 50, Item 1)
        - Jean Dubos, undated; (1 side of 1 sound cassette) (Box 50, Item 2)
        - Ernest Menten, undated; (3 sides of 2 sound cassettes) (Box 50, Item 3)
        - Jean Dubos and Ernest Menten, undated; (1 side of 1 sound cassette) (Box 50, Item 4)
        - Pierre Vivant, 1981 January 22; (1 side of 1 sound cassette) (Box 50, Item 5)
        - Cecile Goldscheider of the Musée Rodin, 1979; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 50, Item 6)
          (In French)
        - Kirk Varnadoe, 1980 May 14; (1 sound cassette) (Box 50, Item 7)
        - Pierre Vivant, undated; June 1979; (7 sound tape reels) (Box 50, Item 8)
          (Identified within recordings as camera reels 315, 316, 318, 320, 322, 326, 357; location of camera reels unknown)
        - Pierre Vivant, 1981 May 10-11; (2 sound cassettes) (Box 50, Item 9)
      - Sculptors at Storm King, 1992-2000; (5 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 50, Item 10)
        (Includes multiple versions; also known as Peter Stern's Storm King)
      - Peter Stern Interview, 2000; (1 videocassette: VHS, silent) (Box 50, Item 11)
      - Book of Kells, 2000; (2 videocassettes: VHS, 1 videocassette: Betacam SP) (Box 50, Item 12)
      - Citibank Commerical, undated; (1 videocassette: VHS) (Box 50, Item 13)
      - Matteo Ricci, 1991; (1 film reel) (Box 50, Item 14)
      - Unidentified Sound Cassette, undated; (1 sound cassette) (Box 50, Item 15)
    - Projects by Others (Box 51)
      - Buffalo Rock, undated; (1 film reel) (Box 51, Item 1)
      - Eames and Lipchitz, undated; (1 videocassette: VHS) (Box 51, Item 2)
        (Contains films by Charles and Ray Eames and copy of Bassett's Lipchitz film)
      - John F. Kennedy News Films (Box 51)
        - President Kennedy's News Conference #12, 1961 June 28; (1 film reel) (Box 51, Item 3)
          (Contains transcript)
        - Conversation with President Kennedy, 1962 February 7; (2 film reels; oversized reels in Box 66) (Box 51, Item 4)
      - Man is My Name by Pierre Dominique Gaisseau, 1969-1970; (1 film reel; oversized reel in Box 66) (Box 51, Item 5)
      - The Man with Two Sides to His Head by Anthony Cave Brown (Box 51)
        - Draft of Screenplay, undated; (3 of 5 folders) (Box 51, Item 6)
        - Draft of Screenplay, undated; (2 of 5 folders) (Box 52, Item 1)
        - Research, undated (Box 52, Item 2)
      - NBC Experiment in Television: Dream on Monkey Mountain, part 2, 1970; (1 film reel; oversized reel in Box 67) (Box 52, Item 3)
    - Oversized film reels, Conversation with President Kennedy (2 film reels from Box 51, item 4) (Box 66)
    - Oversized film reel, Man Is My Name by Pierre Dominique Gaisseau (from Box 51, item 5) (Box 66)
    - Oversized Unidentified Video (from Box 49, item 12) (Box 67)
    - Oversized film reel, NBC Experiment in Television: Dream on Monkey Mountain, part 2 (from Box 52, item 3) (Box 67)